So I would say I I exclude the
possibility of consciousness as we would
conceptualize it in humans simply as a
consequence of ever more computing
power. That being said, I would say that
if we take that notion of consciousness
away from a definition of AGI, I would I
would be open and I think it's pro it's
probable that we will have a form of AGI
not conscious, right? in which is uh
applicable across a general domain right
not just a narrow form of AI right but I
think we should separate the two notions
of just because it's artificial general
intelligence right it's not the kind
that we often see in science fiction
which I do think in many cases is
prophetic you know things like westworld
or exmachina uh we see a lot of the
risks father was already talking about
the risk of relationality right we ever
ever more we're seeing that as AI I is
managing to simulate right uh ever uh
ever better that assimulating at the
level of even intimacy but the problem
there is that it's intimacy without
presence right so you know Peter krief
if I if I remember the sitation well he
said there's no one there right because
we tend to look at performance surf
surface level performance as a nexus a
locust for intimacy right so we get ever
more connected we're really becoming
ever or isolated.
>> Um Stephen and and Father John, thank
you so much for for being here with us
today. Could you tell us a little bit
about I guess the progress I hope that's
being made across these these two days
at at the forum with regards to AI and
consciousness?
>> Sure. Um I think it was one of the most
interesting of the the breakout groups
that we have the that being the one I am
participating in which is on Catholic
touring test and that's you know between
quotation marks because what is exactly
that means we're not really excluding
any idea so we're kind of doing if if we
want to use an analogy a cenotal process
of listening right and of course you
have stronger voices you have maybe more
introverted voices that are really there
just trying to listen maybe they'll
throw some idea in so we're not really
excluding any possibilities
And we're seeing a lot of tension with
uh like we've discussed before there's a
little bit of a solopism when we start
talking about the idea of consciousness
right and whether it's even technically
possible and if it is if we could open
the realm of possibility to even the
very idea what are the ethical moral and
especially anthropological implications
from a Catholic perspective and just
before coming here I just threw the bomb
out into the room and I said maybe if
we're going to be talking about Catholic
touring test or a test of any kind
because we've excluded the notion of a
of a touring test because we said that's
essentially just surface level mimicry.
There's no interiority there. Let's just
cast that out. Is there any other types
of test for what a Catholic would call
consciousness? And I said we should
begin with a Catholic anthropology.
>> And Stephen, maybe just before we start
to unpack those those questions, what is
a turning test in in the in the simplest
mode, you know, for our audience who
might not know?
>> Yeah. So developed by Alan Turring in
the 50s with uh touring machines. So
rudimentary computers essentially if I
could distill it down just to make it
easy for those who are not familiar with
computing is if you can't tell if a if a
human user uh speaks with uh an
interlocutor uh on a screen. So they're
not seeing the person face to face,
right? If uh they are not if they cannot
distinguish between the responses they
see on the screen as being uh human or
coming from a machine. So if they are
convincing enough that they are human
well what what does that say about the
machine itself right uh what does that
mean? What kind of responsibility do we
have once we arrive at that conclusion
that I cannot distinguish between the
responses as being from a human or being
from a machine. Now that that's why we
were discussing that is that brings up
notions of consciousness and essentially
if if a machine can do that what kind of
responsibility would we have towards it
and you have uh other issues that come a
lot of legal issues of course in terms
of personhood and so on.
>> What do what do you say to someone who
might be confused in that manner or
might be genuinely you know thinking
that they're in some type of
communication with these
>> Yeah. So on one level I think we have to
admit that this is like a very human
response. I mean we have this tendency
of anthropomorphizing almost everything
right from the headlights in a car you
know looks like a smiley face or a sad
face to you know your pets right um and
when we speak to our pets we speak to
our pets in different ways and um and we
form almost this quasi human right bond
um with our pets and you can even say
that through different tools I mean uh
in Europe I don't know if this was a
thing in the states we had the
tamagotchi yeah so
>> I had him too right so those were also
like like a type of pseudo relationship,
right? In a sense, in all these things,
um, these examples I've mentioned, it's
very clear that the thing you're
engaging with is not a human and cannot
fully understand you, right? Um, so if
it's your Tamagotchi pet, if it's your
real pet, your dog, your cat, or if it's
the headlights in a car, right? Um but
now it's it's much more worrying because
now this tendency that we have as humans
to anthropo anthropomorphize
um is is we've put so much gasoline on
the on on that flame right where we have
these tools that are really great at
answering back right um and especially
it's it's not a question of whether the
machine is intelligent or not in fact
Alan Turing back came up with the test
precisely because he thought asking
whether a machine is actually
intelligent is actually conscious is too
difficult to question to ask. So we
should just be concerned with whether it
can uh deceive a human being into
thinking that it's conscious or thinking
that's it's intelligent. Um so this
cause a lot of problems right? I mean
we're we're forming bonds of um of love
affection of care of empathy with an
entity that is not able uh to experience
to feel to express love care empathy and
affection. Right? Um so in a sense
you're you're closing yourself up and on
one level one of the things um one
technical way that we can say the
individual who's doing this is harming
themselves is is we we like to talk
about moral skills. So moral skills is
it's this concept used not just within
the church but but around of these a
different word would be human skills or
interpersonal skills right so we learn
these skills when we're at school
sharing with others um being empathetic
respecting authority voicing your
opinion if you don't agree in a safe way
right so these are moral skills whereas
since we learn them in our interactions
with other people and the image I like
to use is you know the beautiful pebbles
you see on the beach they're smooth and
beautiful because they have rubbed with
other pebbles and the pro is becoming
smooth and beautiful right so whereas so
if I'm not doing this rubbing right uh
with other people and therefore forming
ourel in the skills becoming this
beautiful smooth pebble um but instead
speaking just with an AI chatbots right
and we know right I mean we don't need
to prove this anymore because it's been
proven that these tools are sick ofantic
these tools um do not reflect the truth
these tools are there just to maybe
heighten uh what your opinion is and and
are there to really eagerly please you
So when you have no conflict, no sense
of of uh maybe you know growing and
growth or maturity in these
relationships right uh you're you you're
not going to become a smooth pebble. uh
you're not going to form yourself uh as
a human being you know on these small
skills and therefore this is detrimental
to you in the long run but you know
Stephen maybe in let's say 5 years 10
years when we keep making these
innovations and we keep arriving at um
you know at maybe AGI or ASI you know
will will will the AI in that sense be
conscious I mean that's you know that's
that's what I hear at least you know you
hear that in Silicon Valley um people
are saying 2030 watch out everything
will change how how do you respond to
that
>> well I would say that uh I exclude the
notion of consciousness however we want
to describe it we can describe it for
example uh given my philosophical and
somewhat theological background I would
tend to adopt the a definition of the
awareness of self as self in the act
right so not just awareness of myself
but myself as a subject of experience
right so I would say that it's not a
question of degree because if it was a
question of degree then the
materialistic framework which is
essentially where that uh philosophical
position of we just need more computing
power or we need a different kind of
computing power. People say well now
with the the advent the introduction and
the exponential growth and research of
quantum computing in which now we could
superimpose ones and zeros. I say that
there's nothing actually uh there's no
change of kind in that type of computing
power there. It's not simply about
having more memory. It's not simply of
making it even more recursive, right? or
more the statistical probability field
that an LLM produces arriving rather
than a 60% probability of next token
closer to 100 that does not say anything
of a different kind right so I would say
I I exclude the possibility of
consciousness as we would conceptualize
it in humans simply as a consequence of
ever more computing power that being
said I would say that if we take that
notion of consciousness away from a
definition of AGI. I would I would be
open and I think it's prob it's probable
that we will have a form of AGI not
conscious right in which is uh
applicable across a general domain right
not just a narrow form of AI right but I
think we should separate the two notions
of just because it's artificial general
intelligence right it's not the kind
that we often see in science fiction
which I do think in many cases is
prophetic you know things like westworld
or exmachina uh we see a lot of the
risks father was already talking about
the risk of relationality right we ever
ever ever more we're seeing that as AI
is managing to simulate right uh ever uh
ever better that assimulating at the
level of even intimacy but the problem
there is that it's intimacy without
presence right so you know Peter krief
if I if I remember the sitation wall he
said there's no one there right because
we tend to look at performance surf
surface level performance as a nexus
this locust for intimacy, right? So, we
get ever more connected. We're really
becoming ever more isolated.
>> What do you think that's going to do to
to us as as as people, to us as society
to be surrounded by these by these
embodied AIs, by these images, by these
performances that are at the core empty?
Um, we have a statistic in Mortal, which
is 50% of all people feel feel lonely,
>> feel lonely. So, we're in this age where
we're the most connected yet half of the
people feel lonely, right? So, there's a
mismatch here or there's something that
that we're not doing wrong, right? Or
this connectedness isn't really um
cashing out, right? Um and I think the
word I turn to again and again and again
is incarnation. I mean, our faith has
this central mystery, the central
reality of the incarnation. Um and
another word sometimes I I use an
alternative word instead of incarnation
with people who maybe are outside of
church which is inefficiency
right uh and when you think about the
way uh God chose to save humanity God
chose to save humanity in a very
inefficient way right uh Christ had to
be born 9 months in the womb 30 years
doing what what what was Jesus doing
these 30 years right and then three
years and and I'm sure if if Jesus had a
campaign manager you know taken him to
so many more cities, so many more towns
maybe outside of Israel, right? Um, so
the incarnation tells us something about
the importance of inefficiency or at
least particular types of inefficiency.
I think we're trying to uh, you know, be
efficient on the things we should be
inefficient about. So when you're
spending time with a friend, with your
wife, with your husband, right, with
your children, with your parents, uh,
not doing anything in particular, maybe
just cooking, right? H sure you could go
to a restaurant or a machine can prepare
you know like a concoction of the exact
uh minerals and uh you know vitamins
that you need but you're cooking
together you're wasting time if you're
doing poetry if you're drawing something
if you're sitting down enjoying a glass
of wine smoking a cigar before and
watching the sunset right you're doing
something very inefficient h but it's
it's the thing that builds you up right
it's the thing that that because
precisely you're being in touch with
your humanity and you're building
humanity
>> but it seems that everything we're doing
everyone And everyone that's working on
these problems is trying to do the
opposite. They're trying to make us more
efficient, more isolated, more optimized
in those senses. But I feel that in that
sense we we become more like the robots.
>> Yeah. I mean obviously maybe to be clear
right there's nothing bad with
efficiency but I think efficiency in the
right place, right? So if we can clear
away the tedious things, the things that
really take us away from maybe more
human things. Um so ideally you know we
all have time to spend with our family
with our friends you know doing the
things that are meaningful to us. Uh so
that would be the idea. Uh obviously I
think because of we can forget AI for a
moment right because of the wider kind
of culture we live in at least in the
west right of uh marked by capitalism
marked by productivity you know h so
you're not being productive we have tied
dignity and value your worth as a human
person is on how productive you are. So
we see this when we have discussions
about people who are elderly right
you're no longer able to work therefore
you're of you're a burden to society
right so if your value right or people
are telling us we're growing in a in a
in a culture where my value is tied to
my productivity right which is already
we're starting off from a from bad
premise which therefore leads to the
rest of the the things we see in the
culture around us right so I think it's
again and this existed before you know
this massive surge in AI and all of that
right so I think Maybe um part of the
solution is also in tackling the wider
contextual millia and contextual um
maybe cultural philosophy. Maybe
>> if I may, it seems you what you're
really touching on is kind of a
resurgence of an old Christian heresy
palagianism. It's the through my works
exactly I can save myself.
>> Yes.
>> Right. So in a world which is distinct
which is identifiable with a crisis of
meaning and we could say that that's
what would uh how to characterize the
west more broadly that in that vacuum of
meaning that's why we see the the re the
surge the the best sellers on the on the
bookshelves and the the bookstores are
the self-help books.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Or or and the more
recent you knowism would be in a
different way but they're having a
similar effect would be the process and
work ethic. Right. Yeah. Again, um if
your value is your work, your
productivity, uh which is something that
can be measurable, once again, we're
back to what I was saying before, right?
Spending time with your family, not
productive,
>> how do we how do we make progress? How
do we how do we on some level help, you
know, the the materials kind of
understand and come closer to our point
of view?
>> So, um I said that we risk speaking past
each other and I think some of that has
happened and it's probably uh natural
when we don't really start with first
principles, right? So when we don't have
definitions of terms, term like
consciousness we haven't settled on.
Right. Exactly. Uh could be used with
more than one meaning and we may be
actually speaking about the same thing
by using the word in two different ways.
So we speak past each other. Right.
>> And and Stephen, could you start by
maybe like helping our audience
understand like what what is the
Catholic, you know, understanding of
consciousness?
>> Yeah. So uh I would say if we start with
a proper Catholic anthropology, we would
say that the au uh the perfect union of
body and soul, right? I saw a type of
hyomorphism, the freedom of the will and
that that freedom of the will is
oriented towards the true and the good.
I would adopt the law again and I would
say that a distinguishing feature of the
human is the pure unrestricted desire to
know. Right? And that desire to know is
always oriented towards the truth. In
fact, that's the leap of faith that
undergirds all science. If scientists
didn't believe that there was a truth to
which they were working which cannot be
proved by the scientific method itself
it precedes it it undergurs it right
there would be no ground into the
scientific enterprise at all right it's
that uh pioneering spirit that that we
all have right that I think that AI
could never have right it does not have
the desire right towards the truth so I
would say once we accept these at least
these three facets that undergur uh
which I think is a rather comprehensive
anthropology I think then we can
actually start taking principal
positions. So for example if we I I
propose maybe even like a pastoral
orientation as a kind of first
principle. So things like ministry,
things like the sacraments, right? Uh
they require these three things which
means you only a person could do it. If
you ask Chad GPT, pray for me. Its
response will be to compose a prayer,
but only a person can actually pray for
you, right? Chad GPT is not capable of
that. It doesn't matter if it has
quantum computing behind it. Doesn't
matter if the response is instant,
right? It doesn't have to do the
thinking dot dot dot, right? No, that
doesn't matter, right? So we have to
start I think with uh a robust
anthropology get our terms very very
clear and then once we're speaking the
same language so we don't risk speaking
past each other then we can start
building from there.
I think if I can I'm fully agree. Um and
I think there are maybe some lacunas in
Catholic anthropology in its expression
not in its content. Um, so for example,
an example I go to again and again is,
you know, something central which kind
of groups all of the things we're
talking about is that man is created in
the image of God, right? And the central
element of our faith and our theology,
right? But if you look at the catechism
of the Catholic Church, it expresses the
definition of being created in the image
of God in terms of a number of
functions. Human being is created in the
image of likeness of God. That is to
say, with the ability to enter into
communion, um, be able of
self-possession and a couple of other
things. And this might create a problem.
You back on the Turing test kind of
thing. Exa again. Right. Because we
might have a machine that can imitate
being in communion with you and with
Right. Exactly. So um that is maybe a
bit of a lacuna where as church given
these new realities we need to express
in a better way right to kind of bring
to the four what is the central thing
that we're trying to say and the church
is already trying to do that. So uh you
mentioned relationality right? So one of
the uh one of the recent landmark
documents of the church is Antiqua,
right? Published in January. Um and the
first one-third of that document really
delves into detail on how we as human
beings are so much more fleshed out, you
know, maybe pun intended there, uh than
just machines, right? People who compare
AI to human beings or it's like a human
being. We really have a reductive view
and a poor view of what human beings
are. and you know the search for the
truth, this this idea of of stewardship
of the word relation, our embodiment,
right? These are all different things
which together compose the beauty and
the privilege and the dignity of being
human as opposed to a simple machine.
>> Um Stephen, when when you're, you know,
when you're in that session and they're
talking about, you know, these themes,
what what would what in your estimation
would a good Catholic framework look
like? I uh I would say we could probably
if we want to maintain or conserve the
language of touring test which I think
is as we already mentioned the both of
us we already discussed at the beginning
is essentially a uh a way to determine
how good it is at mimicking right how
good it is at deceiving or being
deceived right maybe it does not because
I I I would contend there is no
intentionality there the system is not
trying to deceive you are deceived right
you allow yourself to be deceived right
>> says more about the person than about
the thing that is Yeah, they're
communicating with it, right? Um, so I
would say invert it, throw it entirely
on its head. Um, the system could be a
form of constitutional AI, right? Where
yes, it's true and we've discussed this
in our working group that the the the
sheer number of parameters of large of
the very the very big large language
models, but this goes even for the
smallest ones, right? Right? We're
talking about something around 3 to 6
billion parameters for the small ones.
Right? So that's even in principle we
could say that although not logically
impossible but in effectively impossible
for any human to be able to keep into
account all those parameters. So that's
that classic blackbox way of speaking,
right? But if you can translate a
constitution into symbolic logic, so
it's formal symbols, right? The system
despite being blackbox, despite only
providing a field of probability that
the transformer can select from that, it
has to reference first to the
constitution. If the the output that it
gives does not correspond to the logic
of this immutable constitution, it feeds
back into the system until it can uh it
can become valid within the framework
there. Catholic social teaching, right,
and dogma provides a 2,000-year history
of formal teaching that could be in
principle translated by logicians into a
uh a formal constitution that could then
mitigate some of the risks that we tend
to attribute to AI because of this
opacity, the inability to look into the
black box and see what's going on there,
right? But that always means we have to
begin with an orientation with our first
principles an ontological
uh position that says that the human
being is even distinguished by pure
unrestricted desire to know right with
intentionality which systems do not and
I content cannot ever possess right um
even an epistemic position which we've
seen with anthropics uh most recent
paper concerning introspection there
right I would say that that that's still
problematic, right? But even if you can
fix all the tweaks, that says nothing of
the system itself. It does not
demonstrate intentionality there, right?
And we have no reason to the principle
of parsimony would force us to not
attribute more complexity to where the
to where we we don't have reason to,
right? Um and then the third is the
pastoral position that that I mentioned.
So we begin with a Catholic
anthropology. We shouldn't try to
recreate the wheel there. We have the
history. We have the dogma that could be
translated into logic that could be used
to constrain many of the risks that are
that are tended to be attributed to
these kinds of opaque systems.
>> At least I feel like I've seen this even
in my mode of speaking when if I spend
all day working, you know, and I'm
using, you know, let's say chat or
something and I come back home and I
start to talk as if I'm talking, you
know, you realize, oh, wait a second. I
I'm using certain words differently. I'm
starting to, you know, quantify my time
and say, sweetheart, I have 30 minutes.
Let's go. Like, what do we what are the
high points? control.
>> What what are the what you know what are
the high points of low and you realize
oh my gosh I am you know and I'm I'm
worried like because I I hear Stephen
when when when he when he's talking
about you know we have to you know this
imitation is not real you know we have
to be able to understand that but then I
I'm I'm also very nervous that okay you
start to have these these robots doing
all sorts of active actions in your in
your day-to-day life and then you you
know that's not good for your soul
either
>> and this is again so so this is whether
whether or not AI becomes conscious or
not right like Stephen I think they
can't um but this is this is this
problem remains right um and it's kind
of going back also to our sort right the
whole habits right so the way we
interact again and again creates a habit
right and we're engaging in a particular
human way at least um whether want to or
not whether we know it or not with
certain AI tools right you talking about
talking to judge that carries on outside
in the world right when we speak with
real people now um so this is This is a
bit of a risk. Um quote that I I I I
always bring to mind is a quote by St.
Benedict his rule. Um and I I was at a
conference here at the Vatican um a year
or so ago and and someone made this
comment and and so it's not my idea but
but this remained in my head and it's
beautiful. Um so the the the quote was
from the part in the rule of St.
Benedict where he's talking about the
person who looks after the uh the
kitchen. All right. It's a very
important role in the in the monastery
and uh in in Bendix's rule he says um
the this the monk in charge of the
refree must treat all the utensils as if
they were uh instruments and tools used
on the altar. Right? So must use the
treat the treat the the bowl the cups
the the forks and knives as if they were
the chalice the pattern uh the chaborium
the amples right which is interesting.
So what he's trying to get at is oh that
they're holy but we should we should use
these tools in the same sense of
reverence and you know and then and um
and I maybe this might be something we
should carry on now not to engage with
judgy as if you talk to a priest or
maybe you know use these tools as if you
know not saying that they are right
obviously tools of the altar tools of
the altar not really a phrase but anyway
um but I think with that sense of of of
awareness right that um conscious of
what it does to me you're talking about
the cultivation of the virtues. Yeah.
Exactly. So you make the good first
possible so then it becomes easy.
>> Exactly. So, so the the maybe what I
want to highlight here exactly what
you're saying Stephen is is we're doing
this not because we believe that there's
some inherent dignity in charge or in
these air tools but in treating in using
these tools in a respectful way this
helps us build our virtue right so maybe
a simplistic form of this is whether you
should say please or thank you to Chad
or those Saman said something about this
a few months ago um so I think you
should say please and thank you to Chad
not because Chadi is deserving of your
kindness and politeness, but because
this cultivates a habit within us, this
cultivates a virtue within us, which in
turn we kind of engage with and the real
people we talk to. Right. So, uh there's
an argument there to be said about that.
Absolutely. Right. Um but again to
highlight not because of some inherent
value or or dignity um or any adjacent
concept that we should ascribe to these
tools, but because of the way it helps
us grow in our formation and our
cultivation of virtue. what practical
next steps do you want to see done? So I
think uh on a few on a few fronts and
thankfully the builder's AI forum has a
number of workshops that seem to have
anticipated some of these launching of a
thousand ships as Matthew Sanders
mentioned that's the goal right it's not
to come up with a single constitution or
a single rule a set of guidelines
already a lot of them is everyone out on
their own right to preach to all nations
right so I think that well at least
coming from uh the workshop shop that
that I'm directly involved in at least
some sort of deliverable so that we can
start speaking at least the same
language. Right? So set the the bar a
little bit lower there. Fundamentally,
it it's probably going to touch more on
education because when we converged on
similar ideas in our workshop, which was
not on education, was that there seems
to be a lack of common understanding,
right? The risks of anthropomorphizing,
but also the benefits to the one that
anthropomorphizes. Like as we said, that
says less about the system that we
anthropomorphize and more about the
empathy felt, right, projected from the
person doing it, right? So those types
of costs and benefits should be
communicated and that's done through
formation and through education. So I
think that that's going to be kind of
the the long term, but that has to start
today, right? That that that should have
started yesterday, right? That kind of
formation uh and ministry talking about
AI this morning at mass. Um the father
spoke about the builder's AI forum,
right? And he managed to bring in
Renaissance art as an analogy to uh what
we're doing today, right? We have to go
forth. And I and I think that there's a
lot of um optimism even from my part,
even from the fact that I'm coming from
a workshop where there's a lot of
disagreement, a lot of tension. Um I I'm
still optimistic. I think that we can
produce something that when we leave uh
Rome today uh that we can bring with us
and we can actually make some sort of
change even to a small degree.
>> I think awareness of of anthropology,
you know, this word we're going to again
this morning we received a beautiful
message from Pope Leo, right? addressed
to to to us I suppose right to the
participants of the of the builders
forum um and there was it was all very
beautiful a short message but but
fantastically and there was there was a
quote that struck me as uh Father was
reading the message which is um
obviously I don't remember it by heart
but something along the lines of every
decision we take um uh even a question
of design even design the way a tool is
designed expresses something of our
vision of humanity
our vision of our idea of it but our
vision for it right so I think to imbue
this this this awareness this framework
of our anthropology right of who the
human being is his dignity uh his
faculties and therefore the lack thereof
of AI right the way we express if it's
design if it's the way we run companies
right if it's the way we think of risk
mitigation and risk assessment um if
it's if it's the way we speak of
education in the former sense of
schooling right if we speak of I mean
there's a workshop on healthcare. The
way we want to preserve the therapeutic
relation between healthare worker and
patient as opposed to just treating that
again as a process, right? Anthropology,
our version of anthropology should be
imbued. Our vision of humanity and for
humanity should be imbued in all these
different uh steps of the process and
all the different aspects maybe or
economies if you will where AI is
involved. And I think that would be if
if you know the the builders forum
manages to get everyone on board and we
are I mean we're all Azure is just maybe
I think you know pushing it out there
that will be the greatest thing we would
do I think.
>> Well on that very positive note uh
Father John Stephen thank you so much
for all the important work that you're
doing and I wish you all the best on
this final day at the Builder AI forum.
>> Thank you for inviting. Thank you.